[SPEAKER_03]: This is in Gautama Nikaya, book of 11, sutta number 9, called Vissanda.
[SPEAKER_03]: At one time, the Buddha was staying in Jnatika, in the brick house.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, Venerable Sanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Buddha said to him, Sanda, meditate like a thoroughbred, not like a wild colt.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like a thoroughbred would be a well-tamed horse, and a wild colt would be like an untamed horse.
[SPEAKER_03]: And how does a wild colt meditate?
[SPEAKER_03]: A wild colt tied up by the feeding trough meditates.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fodder, fodder.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like, he's just concerned with his food, with the hay that that's given to him.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it doesn't occur to the wild colt tied up by the feeding trough, what task will the horse trainer have me do today?
[SPEAKER_03]: How should I respond?
[SPEAKER_03]: Tied up by the feeding trough, it just meditates.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fodder, fodder.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the same way, take a certain untrained person who has gone to the forest, the root of a tree, or an empty hut.
[SPEAKER_03]: Their mind is overcome, admired in sensual desire, and they don't understand, as it is, the escape from arisen sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_03]: Harboring sensual desire internally, they meditate and contemplate and cogitate and ruminate.
[SPEAKER_03]: Their mind is overcome by ill will, indolence and lethargy, restlessness and anxiety, doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Harboring doubt internally, they meditate and contemplate, and cogitate and ruminate.
[SPEAKER_03]: They meditate dependent on earth, water, fire, and air.
[SPEAKER_03]: They meditate dependent on the extent of infinite space, infinite consciousness, nothingness, or neither perception nor non-perception.
[SPEAKER_03]: They meditate dependent on this world or the other world.
[SPEAKER_03]: They meditate dependent on what is seen, heard, thought, cognized, attained, sought, or explored by the mental faculty.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how an untrained person meditates.
[SPEAKER_03]: And how does a thoroughbred meditate?
[SPEAKER_03]: A fine thoroughbred tied up by the feeding trough doesn't meditate, fodder, fodder.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it occurs to the fine thoroughbred tied up by the feeding trough.
[SPEAKER_03]: What task will the horse trainer have me do today?
[SPEAKER_03]: How should I respond?
[SPEAKER_03]: Tied up by the feeding trough, they don't meditate fodder, fodder.
[SPEAKER_03]: For that fine thoroughbred regards the use of the goad as a debt, a bond, a loss, a misfortune.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the same way, take a certain fine thoroughbred person who has gone to the forest, the river tree, or an empty hut.
[SPEAKER_03]: Their mind is not overcome and mired in sensual desire, and they understand as it is the escape from arisen sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_03]: Their mind is not overcome by a will, indolence and lethargy, restlessness and anxiety, doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: They don't meditate dependent on earth, water, fire and air.
[SPEAKER_03]: They don't meditate dependent on the extent of infinite space, infinite consciousness, nothingness or neither perception nor non-perception.
[SPEAKER_03]: They don't meditate dependent on this world or the other world.
[SPEAKER_03]: They don't meditate dependent on what is seen, heard, thought, cognized, attained, sought or explored by the mental faculty.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yet, they do meditate.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, this is basically the most important part.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: There we have it.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Buddha is explicitly advising against any type of absorption meditation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what does it mean?
[SPEAKER_03]: We can start with...
[SPEAKER_03]: There's no description or discussion of what mindfulness is, because oftentimes mindfulness nowadays is regarded precisely as that, as a type of absorption on one thing, or at least sort of focused attention on one thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Usually the breath or bodily sensations, body scanning, and even thoughts, which all of that is included by what the Sutta said, what is sensed, cognized, thought, explored by the mental faculty.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's like literally anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and people think that samādhi is like absorption.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, in the Noble Eightfold Path, it talks about sati, mindfulness, and then samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, people think mindfulness is about focusing on something, which then naturally has to result in the samādhi, which is the absorption of that thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fixed state, when the focusing has been consummated.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, what... let's say...
[SPEAKER_03]: Mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if it isn't about focusing, if it isn't about just looking at what's in front of you, like the wild colt is just looking at the hay that's in front of him, and instead it says the thoroughbred,
[SPEAKER_03]: He wonders about something that's broader than what's in front of him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he still meditates, but not on, as it says there, earth, water, fire, air, or what is being perceived, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so you can see the list is... when you see these kinds of lists in the suttas, like in Majjhima Nikaya 1, where lists basically every possible permutation of anything, that means there is no
[SPEAKER_03]: There's no object or thing that would be good for you to focus on.
[SPEAKER_03]: The right mindfulness is the opposite direction of that, which is exactly what it says.
[SPEAKER_03]: The horse takes a step back from what's actually going on and discerns a broader context.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the principle of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So... and I think people often don't realize that
[SPEAKER_03]: They do have mindfulness, or a certain principle of mindfulness, underlying their everyday actions, which is what allows them to function.
[SPEAKER_03]: But nevertheless, because of the views nowadays, it gets conceived as this basically artificial, contrived practice, that nobody would do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Unless you tell them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas, sometimes, you already have mindfulness and you may not even realize it, because you think it's something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, maybe we should start there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That mindfulness is not something that you fully have to create from scratch.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's basically already a structural aspect of experience that needs to be understood and developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, so, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: I thought of giving an example.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when you have, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: When you, let's say, go to a supermarket, and you know what you have to buy, it's one specific thing, and you're supposed not to spend too much time in the supermarket.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're supposed to be... go somewhere else, and there's a certain deadline there, time constraint.
[SPEAKER_03]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: There are going to be lots of distractions in the supermarket, and you would have at the back of your mind a sort of perspective of this is what I need to buy, and I need to be out of here in 15 minutes.
[SPEAKER_03]: And even though your perceptions are occupied with
[SPEAKER_03]: The things that you're seeing in the supermarket, which might not be the thing that you are specifically looking for, you're walking around, looking through the different aisles and whatnot, and eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: Your perception is... like these are the fodder, like the wild horse is what's in front of you, the things that you're seeing, but at the back of your mind you have this context of why you're actually there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so that's what's actually allowing you to, you know, when you see, I don't know, something that you would have otherwise become distracted by, captivated by,
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't, because you have that broader context in mind, even though you did see the perception.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not that you, sort of like, blinded yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that is actually a principle of mindfulness, and you realize it's not even something you're doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, it's not not even... because if it were on the level of what you're choosing to attend to, then, immediately, when you choose to attend to the things that are in front of you, which are not what you're looking for, you will lose your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's right.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that already shows that these are two levels happening in your experience, and... At the same time.
[SPEAKER_03]: At the same time, and that level where the memory is, or the context is, that it... that doesn't even require effort.
[SPEAKER_03]: It requires a negative effort, basically, of
[SPEAKER_03]: Not allowing yourself to, as you said, get captivated by anything specific, because if you allow that to happen, then that's when the memory will fade, and you will find, oh, 10 minutes have passed by, and I was just, you know, grabbing all this other stuff that I didn't actually need.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's a basic form of mindfulness that everybody would have, and you would realize some people
[SPEAKER_03]: They have such little amount of mindfulness that they couldn't even fulfill that type of task reliably.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would basically forget why they went to the grocery store, come back home with a bag of stuff, which also didn't contain what they went to the grocery store for to begin with.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, eh... the focusing direction is like... there is some overlap.
[SPEAKER_03]: With you being mindful and you being focused, but the overlap is actually quite small.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, yes, if you every second try to focus on the thought of what you have to get, technically, yes, you won't forget, but you're not actually understanding that the memory
[SPEAKER_03]: Of the context of why you're in the supermarket, that actually endures at a different level of your attention.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're overdoing the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't need to recollect a hundred times, when you have only 10-15 minutes in the supermarket, what it is that you want to get.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is not how it would ordinarily work.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's also because of these views that get imposed over the practice, which is...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's mainly originated from the Abhidhamma and the commentaries that the mind is made up of these discrete moments that follow individually.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, there's... nothing endures for more than one mind moment.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, the view then is, every mind moment needs to have mindfulness in it, like me actively doing that mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because otherwise,
[SPEAKER_03]: I will forget.
[SPEAKER_01]: That results in a rather neurotic take on what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you would realize that type of mindfulness, you will never be able to have it always.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will only be able to have it in periods where you're basically not functioning as a person.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you're just fully sitting down,
[SPEAKER_03]: Absorbed, dedicated to nothing else but the practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, technically, from that point of view, every other moment of your life, as the Buddha said, someone who is not mindful is as if dead.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that means, like, 90% of your time, unless you're on retreat, always, you're being heedless, because you're not mindful, if that's what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas, if you understand it in this way,
[SPEAKER_03]: Which, by the way, that was obviously a mundane example of mindfulness, what I just gave the example of the supermarket, but if we now take it on a more accurate level of the mind and actually make it relevant to the freedom from suffering, you could see, well, you would have the same recollection of, let's say, not acting out of unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we should clear up that there's this difference between focusing on things in front of you and recollecting context, which is what the mindfulness is, as we have now established.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, we need to give some content, quote-unquote, to what is the right context.
[SPEAKER_03]: The establishing of mindfulness is that you do need to attend to it for a moment.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you can't just expect that the context will be already there.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's more like setting it up and that it endures on its own.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the same with this.
[SPEAKER_03]: You do have to, for a moment, think about, okay, I am supposed to leave the supermarket in 15 minutes.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not that if you don't think about it, it will be there on its own.
[SPEAKER_03]: But once you think about it,
[SPEAKER_03]: It just sort of floats there on its own, and you don't need to be constantly... Now, if you find yourself getting distracted, then you need to think about it again.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I'm supposed to get out of here at 9.15 or whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then you bring it back.
[SPEAKER_03]: But throughout the time where that context was there, that mindfulness was there, floating on its own, you don't need to be
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, that would actually distract you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, imagine if you're just totally going in that direction of trying to remember it every second, you won't even be able to pay attention to what's happening in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so you may find actually sort of the product that you're looking for, and you can read the label, pay attention to that, trying to understand what it says, the label of the product, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're not directly attending to that context, but that doesn't mean that you have lost your mindfulness on that occasion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is only when you then stray
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same way, you would have, for example, a context of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I should not act out of an wholesome state.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I shouldn't break the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would go through your life,
[SPEAKER_03]: And many times, you would have moments where you are factually like you're going to work or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't... like you have to pay attention to what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't be thinking about this the whole time.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, you can still be mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And how would you know that you've lost your mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, when you catch yourself making an intention to do something that was... that you had previously determined not to do, then you know, I lost my mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: The thing is, you cannot have like a...
[SPEAKER_03]: You cannot have, like, an external point of view, where you see, like, the mindfulness enduring, and then, this is the second where it's faded.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not how it works.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that would... Then, right there, you pick it back up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: That requires, that would require you to have an external perspective to your own experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: And mindfulness is quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mindfulness is, like, it comes before your point of view.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can't, like, watch it as an object.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why it's saying, like, the bright meditation doesn't depend even on what's explored by the mental faculty.
[SPEAKER_03]: What's explored by the mental faculty comes second to the mindfulness, if it's established properly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you won't even be able to, like, watch it fading.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just you find yourself...
[SPEAKER_03]: After the fact, you can't even trace, like, how long, how much time passed.
[SPEAKER_03]: You find yourself, oh, I lost my mindfulness, because I was about to do something, break a precept, whereby, even though I had determined, I wouldn't do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you have to restart it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: The point is, you don't develop a view that it's about constantly having it there.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's about restarting it or refreshing it when you lose it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the funny thing is, there is a certain sense of the direction of mindfulness that's embedded into a lot of the modern practices, like the noting, for example.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you know, when you're doing something, and then you're telling yourself, sitting, sitting, sitting, walking, walking, walking, bending, bending, bending...
[SPEAKER_03]: The thing is, like, if you were totally oblivious to that broader context of, like, what your body is doing, and then you bring your mind back to that, that is the direction of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the thing is, if you now...
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, you established it, but now you keep attending to it every second.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, now you're overdoing it, because the point was not to... to... like, you actually lost the mindfulness as a result of doing that, because you became absorbed.
[SPEAKER_03]: The whole point of the mindfulness should have been, okay, I am sitting, and now that sort of peripheral image or idea endures in your mind, while it's now... like, we can do it right now, for example, like...
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so, I remember that I am here, sitting down, even while I'm talking, my body is in this position.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, now I'm thinking about other things.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not particularly thinking about my body sitting down, but that memory is still there, enduring.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that, until that body changes posture, for example.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then,
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I haven't thought about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I still haven't forgotten about the fact that I'm sitting.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, that's the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there might be a...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ordinarily, when one hasn't come across the Buddha's teaching, mindfulness is already in a small degree there, as you said in the beginning, as a structural principle, but then people are not developing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But on account of wrong instructions and wrong ideas, those people who are developing mindfulness, there's a high chance that they might actually overdo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now a similar thing occurs to me as well, just to continue with the grocery store.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, suppose somebody has to buy something in the shop, they need to walk there, and they say, well, let's... this is the wrong type of mindfulness, but just as an illustration, and they say, let's use this 10-minute walk to the grocery store to practice mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they pay attention to every time they put their right foot on the ground and every time they put their left foot on the ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they actually pay attention every time they put their foot on the ground for the next 10 minutes.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't miss a single step.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then they find that they actually walked to their friend's house and are about to ring the doorbell there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, did that person now practice mindfulness correctly or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people might say, yeah, because, you know, you were actually, you know, walking, walking, feeling every time my foot's on the ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: I felt it there, so I was there with my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the whole point is, you were too concerned with that narrow, specific...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exercise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Failing to realize that you were just going to do that, because you had something more important to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Namely, to get that item from the grocery store, which somebody has now completely spaced out, and they ended up doing something different.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and also, you often sometimes even hear the view that, like, when you... Oh, I was meditating, and I totally forgot what was happening.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, my concentration was so good,
[SPEAKER_03]: That, like, I didn't even realize that time was passing by or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: I just totally forgot.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's regarded as a good thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas mindfulness is actually awareness.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's quite the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you're so aware that you can't even overlook anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, but on the
[SPEAKER_03]: On that level of your actions, your attention, the mindfulness precedes the attention.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, essentially, it would be impossible for you to say something like, I forgot where I was, or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because if attention is secondary, you would have a memory, or you would be able to recollect what it is that you were attending to, if the mindfulness
[SPEAKER_01]: is more fundamental than whatever it is that you're attending to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the fundamental purpose of mindfulness of the body, which is like the most popular one, because it does, ironically, or unfortunately, allow, or misconceiving it into a kind of absorption or focusing practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: But how do you focus on your mental state?
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is the third satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you focus on feeling, which are not sensations?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you focus on... because it says there, if feelings were sensations, then why does the satipaṭṭhāna sutta says, I know when I experience a feeling of the flesh, I know when I experience a feeling that's not of the flesh, meaning it's not a sensation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how can you focus on the Four Noble Truths?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, all of these things are on that same level of a peripheral context and mindfulness of the body is exactly the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's nothing special.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's the purpose of, for example, the mindfulness of the postures is, like I said, I mean, I've been talking the whole time.
[SPEAKER_03]: I haven't forgotten the fact that I am sitting, even though
[SPEAKER_03]: The mind is going in all sorts of different directions.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's... why... why then... why is it... why would it be beneficial to have that memory of the body there?
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's say the posture that it's in or something like the asubha practice or breathing
[SPEAKER_03]: Why would that be beneficial?
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's not a... now that we've clarified that it's not a focusing... Yeah, so now that we've clarified that body is not an object in front of you that you attend to, but is itself a context that one can recollect, which is one of the right recollections, so now you're asking why is that part of the actual dhamma and why is that wholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any ideas, anyone?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can see that this thing that is like this kind of context of being embodied, you could say, it doesn't require you're putting it there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there whether you're kind of like attending to it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you kind of keep that in the background, then
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever you do, whatever you see, whatever you think of throughout the day, is put into this...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm trying to put this in my own words instead of just using the buzzwords, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess it can just kind of show you that it is not something that is your doing, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not dependent upon your putting it there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And why is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What happens when you don't have that type of perspective?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you kind of just overlook it and take it on as, like, for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, this is...
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess you kind of put yourself there, and you don't... you don't see it as being something that is necessary for whatever you're engaging in, I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for instance, if you're not kind of aware of there being a tongue,
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're like eating, you might kind of act in a heedless way, just kind of like taking on that taste, for instance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas...
[SPEAKER_03]: So when it says, um, harboring sensual desire internally,
[SPEAKER_03]: In relation to that, harboring the hindrances internally, when a person focuses, when a person is just thinking about what's in front of them, like the wild cult, how does... actually establishing the context, like it says they're asking, the horse asking himself, what does the trainer want me to do today?
[SPEAKER_03]: How does that fix that situation of being overcome by sensual desire, aversion, and so on?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's kind of taking a different... it's including that internal aspect within your kind of contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what what happens when it's not included?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in that case, then it is internal and you're kind of... you're there, essentially.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like it's a... you kind of become susceptible to whatever that is susceptible to.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so the point being, you don't need to explicitly be heedless or do anything immoral, do anything bad.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not having mindfulness, in and of itself, opens the way for greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's... the fact of regaining that perspective over your experience,
[SPEAKER_03]: If the perspective is properly established, any of these things, like, what is sensual desire?
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you be sensually obsessed with an object, if you have perspective?
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't, because sensory desire is precisely the loss of perspective.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not the pleasure of the object.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not the perception of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's when you... all of these hindrances, actually.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not the things that arose in your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's when you become absorbed in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and absorption and the right mindfulness, that's a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so...
[SPEAKER_03]: Anything, then, that becomes... that you become absorbed in, automatically introduces one of the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if it's a mental thing that has nothing to do with the usual things that you perceive in the world, if it's just a mental perception during an absorption experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: Desire, that the principle of desire, the principle of wanting, the principle of appropriation, is there for as long as you lack perspective in regard to that thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why, ironically, with this view of absorption, many people would say, in jhāna, you are attached, or you're sort of indulging in this object that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_03]: But actually,
[SPEAKER_03]: The peace comes from the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you withdraw yourself from anything that your attention could have been taken by, while the attention is still there, you don't destroy the attention, but you simply... you basically develop this vantage point.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what, you could say, that's what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mindfulness is like a vantage point, and while everything else is happening here, well, that vantage point is kept.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it doesn't matter that even the content of what's here, you realize all the problems arose because you were here.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't matter what, even if it's a good thing that was down here, if you are there, there is sensual desire, aversion, restlessness, craving of some kind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Craving for more of this pleasant experience that I think is wholesome, but because I'm absorbed in it, well, the principle of wanting more pleasure is still there, and that's what's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I have a question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suppose somebody follows the discussion so far, and they see, okay, mindfulness is not getting lost in that direction, but it's establishing this context, or this spiritual awareness, as you said.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they try to practice that, and they say, it's too vast, it's too spacious,
[SPEAKER_01]: To just dwell on that context, there's nothing really there for me to hold on to.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need something more specific to anchor my mind because I'm too busy, too distracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might work for one or two minutes and then I'm just spaced out for the next two hours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would it not be better to introduce some object in front of me that I can fiddle around with to anchor my mind in that direction first?
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is a very common idea, you know, taught on meditation retreats.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, there's this presumed gradual development of mindfulness there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, there are some risks connected with that, because you are already moving away from the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody finds themselves sort of in between these two domains,
[SPEAKER_01]: What can they practically do to strengthen that context and that understanding without falling back again in the old groove of wanting to be with something in front of you because you think that is how your mind calms down?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what do you think?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I think it's a general thing that we take the Buddha's teaching quite the other way around.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, we start with, like, meditation, sitting, and then we go, oh, maybe I should maybe moderate my eating, maybe my sleep as well, or what my intention is actually, but still, I'm sitting there, and then we come to the precept, maybe one day, and I think if one person find himself, like, that this context, this mindfulness is too spacious for him, it's just because he's doing actively things that prevent him to discern that mindfulness that is already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the thing is, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: This person should realize that it's not so much about doing certain things actively right now, but it's restraining myself for doing things that prevent me to discern what mindfulness is, what we are talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what does somebody, more practically perhaps, need to restrain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because this context, as you actually said in the beginning, it's not that you magically lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a sense, it is because one makes certain choices, that that context, that one falls away, so to speak, from the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how does one prevent that from happening?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is how you can have the openness and the spaciousness, without falling into the absorption of the other direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, not to mystify openness and spaciousness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Again, it's like... it's a...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's something that you already have some experience of.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just that the theme of it is not the right one.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just mundane things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what would a person then practically do to sustain that context?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it depends where this person is, but let's say, like, someone that never heard anything and start right now, it will be, like, respecting the precept and then sensory strength and then so on, like, kind of the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_02]: And... yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also, like, if this person, like, something that I kind of hear a lot as well is, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, I need these people to meditate.
[SPEAKER_02]: I need this group meditation and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's also, like, kind of something that someone should consider.
[SPEAKER_02]: That if he's looking for someone else to be there in order to meditate, that is because he's looking for a reward again.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's hoping for something to... to an experience to arise.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And also, can you keep the precepts if you're not mindful?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that is actually... when it feels like these four satipaṭṭhānas are too difficult, because actually there's a sutta where the Buddha takes even monks, actually, not lay people, and he instructs them in five things that are basic for their training, and none of those five things are the four satipaṭṭhānas.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the precepts, sense-restraint, moderation in eating, restraining their speech, and developing right views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I think it says there, developing seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the instruction for newly going forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But so... Yeah, so, it's along those same lines.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't say develop satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, because satipaṭṭhāna, if you look at the gradual training, that comes already when the person is in the position to abandon the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, yes, the context of the body, feeling, mind, all these things, technically, you could recognize them for a moment, because they are there.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, realistically speaking, if you're not established in these prerequisites, it will be dissipating very quickly, because you haven't even discerned even the mental choices, not just the bodily and verbal choices.
[SPEAKER_03]: The mental choices that you make, that cause that context to dissipate, and then it feels like it just goes by itself, because you're not able to even see your own choices of greed, aversion, and delusion that are
[SPEAKER_03]: That would be the first direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you don't have mindfulness, you simply won't be able to keep sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what the suttas say.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sense restraint cannot be done without mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's not about predetermining a certain set of behaviors that I will never do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, I will never look at this.
[SPEAKER_03]: I will never look at that.
[SPEAKER_03]: As it says, it's specifically, you need to have an awareness of whether
[SPEAKER_03]: States of longing or aversion might arise as a result of what you look at or listen to and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, which means you already need to have a degree of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you're just absorbed, you won't be able to tell which things are
[SPEAKER_03]: Harmful for you to attend to, in which things are not.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, mindfulness would already be involved in that entire practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: And for someone who is starting the training, yeah, that would be more than enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: That would keep them occupied 24-7, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because then you have this desire, okay, I should sit down and focus on an object.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, but are you... are you allowing yourself to... like, why do you take that for granted?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why didn't you...
[SPEAKER_03]: If you just jumped at that thought, it means you already lost the context a long time ago, because you can see that there is some kind of craving involved there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so one's thoughts are also objects in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another thing that we should clarify.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're not just talking about candle flames and pictures of the Buddha on the wall, or on the shrine.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, even your own thoughts, or mantras, or ideas that you dwell on,
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as a test, I think sensed, cognized, and so on, that is still all partaking in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, there will be a context to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Actually, that's a good one.
[SPEAKER_03]: The mantra is like father, father, just replace it with buddha, buddha.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's exactly the same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if you find the wholesome thoughts, let's say you discern, I don't know, a subha, for example, which is, like the Buddha says, this is a beneficial practice.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, people do it as a form of visualization.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, I need to have these images constantly just, like, locking my mind into these mental things that are explored by the mind, as it says there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, various stages of decomposing bodies and stuff like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Keep bringing that image up until, like, it stays there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, magically, that gets conceived as the state of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, eh... it's not even... it's not that at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if, like I said, even if it's a good thing for you to absorb yourself in, like I said, being on the level of objects is the problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not what you are attending to.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the fact that you're attending without mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you attend to anything, even the most superficially wholesome thoughts, but you don't have that vantage point that's at the back of that, peripheral to all that, then, to some extent, the five hindrances are still there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Your mind is still mired in some form of sensual desire, aversion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Actually, if you look closely at these
[SPEAKER_03]: Absorption practices people do, it's actually quite... it's quite stressful.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, they themselves would say, after some time, like, you get tired of... even of the pleasant experiences.
[SPEAKER_03]: They would say, like, oh, the first jhāna, you have this pleasure, and then, at some point, it's just too much.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not how it works in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, like, it's quite interesting, because, like, this kind of absorption practice, like, you come, first time, first session, you sit ten minutes, oh, that's enough, that kind of... And then you do it again next day, and then one week later, you do ten minutes in the morning, ten minutes in the evening.
[SPEAKER_02]: One year later, you find yourself doing one hour in the morning, one hour in the evening.
[SPEAKER_02]: Two years later, you do ten days retreat, ten hours a day.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's exactly like smoking or any single addiction, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just need more and more and more and more and more, not realizing that that attitude is actually what's actually very stressful.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the thing is, you're chasing something.
[SPEAKER_03]: The whole time, you're chasing something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas, this is more like the direction of chasing things.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, it's not like, oh, just let go, relax in the present moment and don't strive.
[SPEAKER_03]: Letting go of chasing takes effort.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's something you have to discern.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, the the attitude of not chasing anything requires, like, the most deep penetrative wisdom.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not like you can't just decide, okay, I will just sit down and I will not crave for anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: It requires that discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because on the most fundamental level, your being, right, that is already... there's already a seeking or a striving.
[SPEAKER_03]: And for as long as there isn't that vantage point that we're describing, the seeking is there automatically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, that's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't need to think to yourself, let me seek something.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just the directionality, the way the mind goes, when there isn't that background, is already towards expectations, anticipations and desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perhaps we should clear up also how this feeds in with what we earlier discussed in the context of yoniso manasikāra, because there are these two directions, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, factor for the right view, yoniso manasikāra, but obviously yoniso is not
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness is also not automatically endowed with attending from that origin, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we should perhaps now bring them together and then see if we can make a move from how this right mindfulness then results in right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that would be the factor that would turn
[SPEAKER_03]: That would allow you to go from just a mundane way of mindfulness, just remembering the things that you're supposed to do throughout the day, would bring you now to actually the Buddha's teaching, yonison manasikāra, because it's now more of an acute establishment where the context is not just another thought that you have there about something in the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's these
[SPEAKER_03]: There are relevant things to your existence that are at the background always.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, the supermarket thing, that you're supposed to do this, that's not there always.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, that's in that specific situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the body, feelings, mind, and phenomena, those things are always there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, those things are even behind, like, even on a deeper layer than these mundane types of mindfulness that you would have.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you would see, whether it's that, being at the grocery store, whether it's sitting down in a room, empty room, body feelings, mind and phenomena have to be there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the origin of anything else that you might attend to.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when that yoniso manasikāra aspect is developed, only then can you get into that dimension of right samādhi, which is
[SPEAKER_03]: By the way, that's the whole point of the Noble Eightfold Path, as it says, is the cultivation of sati, the cultivation of the four satipaṭṭhānas, leads to samādhi.
[SPEAKER_03]: And samādhi would, based on what we're discussing, it becomes clear that
[SPEAKER_03]: Developing that direction would just take you exactly to what it says here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, the mind would become totally independent, even of its own thoughts, even of what's explored by the mental faculty.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have a broader context than that, which is...
[SPEAKER_03]: The body that's always there, the feeling that's always there, those things are behind or underneath anything that you might perceive.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, when that recognition becomes so strengthened, that there is no need for you to even refresh it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, periodically, that you had to do it before.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, even if you just totally try to forget it, you can't.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you see that the experience of forgetting is something that's explored by the mind, which is second to the body that's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you say behind or underneath, something that I find useful to think about that is, say, you have like a structured set of tasks.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're looking for a nail, because... like, you're looking for a nail, because you need to replace, or you need to fix a paintbrush, because you're trying to paint a room, because you're planning to sell this house, for instance.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be looking for that nail,
[SPEAKER_00]: And completely forget that you're doing it, to fix a paintbrush.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, you can kind of have the paintbrush in mind, but forget that you're painting the room.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, kind of, you can kind of see things in this kind of structured way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I guess, the point being...
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I guess I was kind of stacking it up like this, but you said below, not that it matters too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, like, there will be the four satipaṭṭhānas underlying whatever task you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's kind of... You would have to work towards that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that structure is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just in ordinary situations.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you want to push it further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like I said, in the house.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until, at some point,
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to realize, well, because having been born, I'm subject to all day sickness and death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Losing what I now take to be mine is unpleasant, which is bound to happen, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: I have to put up with all sorts of stuff that I don't want.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't always get the things that I do want.
[SPEAKER_01]: In short, I'm a prey to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That... so we... so somebody has to basically go, if they find themselves now searching for a nil, then they can all the way
[SPEAKER_01]: To that context.
[SPEAKER_03]: Although, of course, it's not that it would take time to find it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just that...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not like an intellectual exercise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I really searching for the nail?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's because of my father when I was 12.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, because then you get lost in all sorts of... Well, that's explored by the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're getting absorbed in that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, no, it's... Well, again, the same direction where people start noting things like sitting, sitting, walking, walking...
[SPEAKER_03]: Go in that direction, but without trying to block now, like whatever you're thinking about and whatever you're perceiving.
[SPEAKER_03]: Don't try to replace what you were doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Instead, see those things happening on two different levels, which means you won't be able to keep noting constantly in your mind, because that's going to become an object.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you have that awareness.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like a one percent of
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what we call peripheral.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's kind of like a peripheral vision.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you know, I can be aware of my hands.
[SPEAKER_03]: Here, I'm not looking at them.
[SPEAKER_03]: While I'm looking at you, and I'm discerning the aspects of your face, but I know that my hand is still right here at the same time.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if I now start doing this, now something else becomes peripheral.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you start focusing on sitting, sitting, walking, walking, well, the actual context is now behind that.
[SPEAKER_03]: The actual mindfulness is now behind that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that context is also not fixed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does depend on what it is that one is deliberately attending to.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is part of the mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why you set it up.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have a choice that's called satipaṭṭhāna, setting up of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you have a choice of which of these things you want to use and all of them serve the same purpose.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why exactly, sometimes in the suttas, it wouldn't even matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Things that are seemingly not related to the Four Noble Truths, they would still serve as an instrument for establishing the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you have these huge lists of things in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Four Brahma-vihāras, you have the Four Great Elements, you have...
[SPEAKER_03]: Sometimes even the Buddha would say, for monks, like when you see a woman, regard her as your mother, or your sister, or as your daughter, so that sensual desire won't arise.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: recollection of the Buddha, dhamma, saṅgha, recollection of virtue, recollection of the devas, recollection of rotting bones, like any... basically anything that you can... anything that serves on that... that can be established on that peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, again, it's... what matters is not the content.
[SPEAKER_03]: What matters is the fact that you have that vantage point above everything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's actually the unification of mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is the characteristic of samādhi, ekāgata.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not one-pointedness, as in, I became so dependent on what is seen, heard, cognized, and explored by the mental faculty that I now don't see anything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's you became so aware of that background, that peripheral aspect that endures there, that now, like I said before,
[SPEAKER_03]: Now you don't even need to make the effort to remember it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because in that scenario, in a sense, nothing is left out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So that is actually the one-pointedness, quote-unquote.
[SPEAKER_01]: It talks about the totality of experience that doesn't allow any room for something to be outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is a different kind of mindfulness than focusing on one thing to the exclusion of everything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's how samādhi would help you to see patisampada, which is the simultaneous dependence of two things.
[SPEAKER_03]: You would be able to see then that the point of view or the setup that occurs when you're absorbed is exactly what won't allow you to actually see that simultaneous dependence.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why people who practice absorption think patisampada is like seeing a sequence
[SPEAKER_03]: Of factors arising.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the dhamma is timeless, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, having that setup of two things enduring at the same time, the context and what you're directly attendant to, you start to realize that none of those two directions can fundamentally be taken as yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the sense of, like, you can choose to call it yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, eh... how can it really be yours if it depends on something else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I was just gonna ask that, like, why is it that rightly discerning this principle of dependent origination is going to uproot or efface that sense of self?
[SPEAKER_00]: This is kind of what I was trying to say earlier.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have kind of both aspects, you have perspective on both, then you're not either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be... if you are one,
[SPEAKER_01]: But you see that that one depends on something else, which are not that one that got it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're the other one, it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you get minced in between, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: The thing is, when there isn't that mindfulness established on that right level, even if you choose to say, this is not mine,
[SPEAKER_03]: What you're actually taking is yours, is that sort of point of view, that observer.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But see, whether you realize it or not, it's not even like a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that mindfulness, precisely, is supposed to come before that observer.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the whole point of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like the observer, what's explored by the mind, you would start to see, even that thing that I regarded in myself,
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you have expanded your perspective, this vantage point now allows you to see, wait, that's actually just another phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas before, that phenomenon was still a phenomenon, but because you were focused on what was over there, it seemed like it was more than just a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_03]: This one is more special than the others.
[SPEAKER_03]: That sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can we say that as long as someone tries to make the effort to look something as not mine,
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, like, seeing things as not mine should not... it's a recognition that doesn't take effort.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not something that is actively done.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the five aggregates, which are the main things that you have to understand, are not yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: Five aggregates are never what you're looking at, or at least that's not the aspect that matters.
[SPEAKER_03]: The aspect of the five aggregates is that
[SPEAKER_03]: background aspect of it that's always there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the feeling that's enduring while you're focused on this, the perception that's enduring, the ideas, the notions that are enduring, consciousness fundamentally, is always that background.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, if you think you're watching your object, your consciousness as an object, which people would sometimes think,
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not consciousness anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Consciousness is what's doing the watching.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, like, sometimes there's a view, okay, when you have developed your focusing skills, then you can turn your attention to see consciousness itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you can't see consciousness itself, first of all, and second of all, it's not later that you're supposed to do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: The practice starts with putting the point of view in perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to say, oh, let me focus on this for a little while, to a step, and then I'll switch it over, that's already missing the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: You start by switching it over.
[SPEAKER_03]: That would have been the right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, if you go in the direction of concentration, by that time, like, your mind is already constricted.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, anything you look at, even if you have increased powers of observation, all of it is coming through that directionality of me looking at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even more than before.
[SPEAKER_01]: We actually want to see that that attention is basically also there on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not you attending fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why as well, maybe the last thing we can clear up is
[SPEAKER_03]: There can be no mindfulness by itself, like, in the context of the path.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because usually, it's like, okay, I start with mindfulness and that will take me to right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's knowing what you're supposed to recollect, knowing how you're supposed to recollect, knowing what the context is.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a... that is what allows you to be properly mindful.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, actually, it's more of like...
[SPEAKER_03]: Instead of...
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, I have my idea of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let me start doing it now, so I can get the result of stream entry, or whatever you're aiming for.
[SPEAKER_03]: It should be by understanding what mindfulness is to begin with, I will be able to reach stream entry or whatnot.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like... Let's say, like, your mindfulness practice is like your technique or your form with which you do a certain physical exercise.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if it's just the first day, you see somebody else grabbing the weight, and you go and do the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, now, I'm just going to do this until I get strong.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you never actually took the time to perfect your form.
[SPEAKER_03]: How you actually do the exercise?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you're not even doing it properly.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the... that would be the...
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is going to backfire at some point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that would be the point with...
[SPEAKER_03]: The whole practice, it's like, first of all, in order to gain the right view, your goal should be learn how to do the exercise properly to begin with.
[SPEAKER_03]: But see, the thing is that's boring.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not as fun as, you know, grabbing the five five-pound dumbbell and really focusing on, like, okay, what's my shoulder positioning?
[SPEAKER_03]: Am I... and then, okay, I'm just gonna grab 50 pounds and then I'm just gonna cheat however way I want.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's the... that's why people don't want to do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, well, it's a form of impatience, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's... it ends up backfiring, as you said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's impatience and also, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: People want to do the practice in their own way, the way they like it, the way they... kind of, it feels good, it's nice.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's kind of like I heard, like, one time I was reading a book, and there was this teacher saying, like, oh, yeah, you just take from, like, all the tradition and you make your own pizza.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, like, if you never learn to bake a pizza, that's gonna taste terrible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you're gonna put, like, fish and then whatever else on top, and there's just never gonna be a pizza, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so you actually need to develop your own criteria as to what's right and wrong before you can practice, because there is no guarantee otherwise that you... Yeah, but those criteria obviously have to come from the actual right instruction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it has to be a combination of both, but it's always that... well, that's another context you can develop.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, I don't understand.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a mindfulness that you keep, and if you lose that,
[SPEAKER_03]: You will start then taking for granted things that feel good to you, or seems like it helps, or ignoring the fact that, as the Buddha said, we are enveloped within ignorance, like within an egg.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can't see... you don't see the way out, even if it seems the way out, like the way out for you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Until you're at least a sotāpanna, it's not the way out.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's some form of improving what you feel, but it's not a form of actual disowning, actual ending of craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's...
[SPEAKER_03]: That's one of the mindfulnesses that a person should put first.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why faith, as well, is the first of the faculties.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mindfulness is actually not the first of the five faculties.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's faith.
[SPEAKER_03]: And faith is basically that recognition that I'm always willing to give up what I think is a practice if I come across the instruction of wherever I put faith and saying that that's wrong.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what faith is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.